## SARANSH CHOPRA

🕏 saransh-cpp.github.io | 🗷 saransh0701@gmail.com | 🛅 saransh-cpp | 🗘 Saransh-cpp | 📢 WhiteViolin

#### About

Saransh is an engineering junior who, by day, works on his academic and professional commitments, and by night, develops and maintains open-source research software, which he believes are the key to collaborative and reproducible research.

He is passionate about Research Software Engineering, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Scientific Machine Learning, and Open-Source Research Software.

#### Education

#### Cluster Innovation Centre, University of Delhi

New Delhi, India

Major: Information Technology and Mathematical Innovations

2020 - 2024

 ${\it Minor: Computational Biology}$ 

CGPA 9.40

## Research and Work Experience

#### FluxML, The Julia Programming Language

Remote

Open-source developer and technical writer [Funded by The Julia Programming Language]

May 2022 - Present

Mr. Dhairya Gandhi (Julia Computing)

- Fixing bugs and developing the infrastructure of prominent Julia ML and DL libraries such as Flux.jl (3,700+ stars), NNlib.jl (Neural Network primitives 150+ stars), Metalhead.jl (Computer vision models 270+ stars), and Functors.jl.
- Writing original Machine Learning/Deep Learning tutorials, documentation and API references for FluxML's ecosystem.
- Working closely with doctoral researchers and FluxML maintainers from around the world.

# Institute for Research and Innovation in Software for High Energy Physics (IRIS-HEP), Princeton University

Remote

IRIS-HEP research fellow [Funded by IRIS-HEP]

June 2022 - September 2022

Dr. Henry Schreiner (Princeton University / CERN) and Dr. Jim Pivarski (Princeton University)

- Prepared Vector (85,000+ installs 45+ stars) for v0.9.0, v0.10.0, and v1.0.0 (first major release) by developing new public API, fixing bugs, and building new infrastructure.
- The releases are currently being used by researchers at CERN, Princeton University, and other research institutes to construct 4D jagged (awkward) vectors and perform Just-In-Time compiled vector operations in Python.
- Worked closely with CERN and Princeton researchers to build infrastructures for the HEP ecosystem.

AiView New Delhi, India

Research and development engineer

September 2021 – December 2021

Mr. Geetansh Saxena and Mr. Chappa Sri Vinay

- Developed end-to-end OCR and Object Detection libraries by wrapping the existing technologies for visually impaired people.
- Built a CI/CD pipeline and a REST API for ease of integration with any existing software using FastAPI and Heroku.
- Collected a dataset of human images and their distance from a point by building a stereovision camera.

#### PyBaMM (Python Battery Mathematical Modelling), NumFOCUS

Remote

Google Summer of Code student developer [Funded by Google]

May 2021 - August 2021

Prof. Ferran Brosa Planella (University of Warwick), Dr. Valentin Sulzer (Carnegie Melon University), Dr. Robert Timms (University of Oxford)

- Built an automated Twitter Bot capable of constructing Mathematical Simulations of Batteries, including but not limited to different battery models, parameter sets, chemistries, degradation modes, and experiments.
- Developed a replying functionality to run Mathematical Simulations on command, created a CI/CD pipeline, and followed a micro-services-based architecture.
- Worked closely with post-doctoral research fellows and PyBaMM maintainers from around the world.

#### **Publications**

[Tra+21] T. G. Tranter, R. Timms, V. Sulzer, F. B. Planella, G. M. Wiggins, S. V. Karra, P. Agarwal, S. Chopra, S. Allu, P. R. Shearing, and D. J. L. Brett. *liionpack: A Python package for simulating packs of batteries with PyBaMM*. Journal of Open Source Software, 7(70), 4051. Oct. 2021. DOI: https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.04051.

## Open Source Research Software

**PyBaMM**Member (pybamm-team), Maintainer, and Core Developer - 235,000+ installs - 450+ stars
PyBaMM (Python Battery Mathematical Modelling) solves physics-based electrochemical DAE models by using state-of-the-art
automatic differentiation and numerical solvers.

**Vector**Collaborator and Core Developer - 85,000+ installs - 45+ stars

Vector is a Python 3.7+ library for 2D, 3D, and Lorentz vectors, especially arrays of vectors, to solve common physics

problems in a NumPy-like way.

[SSP] S. Chopra, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. Vector: vector classes and utilities. DOI: 10.5281/zenodo.5942082. URL: https://github.com/scikit-hep/vector.

Flux.jl Member (FluxML) and Core Contributor - 80,000+ installs - 3,700+ stars
Flux is an elegant approach to machine learning. It's a 100% pure-Julia stack, and provides lightweight abstractions on top of
Julia's native GPU and AD support. Flux makes the easy things easy while remaining fully hackable.

**BattBot**Member (pybamm-team), Maintainer, and Core Developer - 130+ followers - 10+ stars
An automated Twitter Bot that Tweets random Battery Mathematical Modeling Simulations and replies to the requested
Battery Simulations.

**liionpack**Member (pybamm-team), Maintainer, and Core Developer - 2,400+ installs - 30+ stars liionpack takes a 1D PyBaMM model and makes it into a pack. You can either specify the configuration e.g. 16 cells in parallel and 2 in series (16p2s) or load a netlist.

#### Other notable contributions

- **DeepXDE**: DeepXDE is a library for scientific machine learning 350,000+ installs 1,200+ stars Implemented utility functions and improved the existing examples on solving partial differential equations using Physics-Informed neural networks.
- Colour: Colour Science for Python 6,007,000+ installs 1,500+ stars
  Implemented the conversion between RGB and HCL colourspaces, along with tests and documentation.
- Scikit-HEP ecosystem: High Energy Physics in Python
  Fixed minor bugs in awkward and hist, added support for coverage in cookie, and wrote new developer pages.
- Scikits.odes: Offers extra ODE/DAE solvers; an extension to ones available in SciPy 160,000+ installs 100+ stars Debugged and fixed the build (which was failing because of setuptools) and removed support for Python 2.7-3.6.

## Posters and Presentations

- [SSP22a] S. Chopra, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. Compiling Awkward Lorentz vectors with Numba. 21st International Workshop on Advanced Computing and Analysis Techniques in Physics Research (ACAT). Poster (upcoming). Oct. 2022. URL: https://indi.to/45Kzq.
- [SSP22b] **S. Chopra**, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. *Constructing HEP vectors and analyzing HEP data using Vector*. 5th International Workshop on Python in High Energy Physics (PyHEP). Presentation. Oct. 2022. DOI: https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7081003. URL: https://indi.to/bPmMc.
- [S C22a] S. Chopra. Python packaging: from stone age to the future. PyDelhi workshop. Presentation. Sept. 2022.
- [S C22b] S. Chopra. Code coverage through unit tests running in sub-processes/threads: Locally and automated on GitHub. 10th Annual Conference on Python Asia-Pacific (PyCon APAC). Presentation. Sept. 2022. URL: https://tw.pycon.org/2022/en-us/conference/talk/243.
- [S C22c] S. Chopra. Code coverage through unit tests running in sub-processes/threads: Locally and automated on GitHub. 21st Annual Conference On Python Europe (EuroPython). Presentation. July 2022. URL: https://ep2022.europython.eu/session/code-coverage-through-unit-tests-running-in-sub-processes-threads-locally-and-automated-on-github.
- [S C22d] S. Chopra. Vector Constructors, documentation, and benchmarks. IRIS-HEP Lightning Talks. Presentation. June 2022. URL: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fLt7BHuASpw.
- [S C21] S. Chopra. BattBot: Mathematical Modeling of Batteries using an automated Twitter bot. 1st International Training Workshop on Python Battery Mathematical Modeling (PyBaMM). Presentation. Oct. 2021. URL: https://www.pybamm.org/training.

## Grants, Prizes and Achievements

o PyCon Acia-Pacific (APAC)'s grant to lead a talk virtually (NT\$3,600)	July 2022
o Shubhra Kar Linux Foundation Training Scholarship (500 recipients worldwide) for	June~2022
contributions to open-source research software (\$695)	

• EuroPython's travel grant to lead a talk in-person (£460)

June 2022

• PyCon Italia's travel grant to lead a workshop in-person (£400 + lodging support)

April 2022

o Faraday Institution's Collaboration Award for contributions to the PyBaMM ecosystem

November 2021

• Won the Elastic hackathon (out of 2500+ registrations) with a Flutter-Node-Google Cloud-ELK (Elasticsearch, Logstash, Kibana) based application

May 2021

(Elasticsearch, Logstash, Kibana) based application

• Discovered an asteroid having a fixed orbit around Sun by analysing the data Pan-STARRS observatory

August 2016

## Projects

releaseup [NLP, Text summarisation, spaCy, Scikit-learn, TF-IDF, Python library]

September 2022

- Releaseup uses an extractive approach for generating release notes from comments and docstrings added between two git tags.
- The Python library has 200+ installs on PyPI, 5+ stars on GitHub, and follows best development practices.

OCRed [OCR, Computer Vision, Tesseract-OCR, NLTK, Python library]

August 2022

- o OCRed provides clever, simple, and intuitive wrapper functionalities for OCRing specific textual materials.
- The Python library has 1,900+ installs on PyPI, 10+ stars on GitHub, and follows best development practices.

ForMente [NLP, Flutter, Dart, FastAPI, Python, Firebase, Firestore, Heroku, GitHub Actions]

une 2022

- o Using Natural Language Processing, ForMente lets you diagnose your feelings in the form of a secure personal diary.
- The NLP model is deployed on Heroku using FastAPI, and the app uses Firebase and Firestore as its backend.

ChaoticEncryption.jl [Image processing, Encryption algorithms, ODEs, PRNGs, Julia package]

.ciid.

- $\circ$  Vectorised image encryption and PRNG algorithms that runs  $\sim 40X$  faster than ordinary nested-for implementations.
- The Julia package has 10+ installs on JuliaHub and 28+ stars on GitHub.

#### PDEsWithPINNs [PDEs, PINNs, Python, DeepXDE]

January 2022

- Worked under Prof. Shobha Bagai to solve 1, 2, 3, and 4D Partial Differential Equations using Physics-Informed Neural Networks.
- Worked with Neural tangent Kernels, Multi-scale Fourier feature networks, and Spatio-temporal Multi-scale Fourier feature networks to predict high-frequency details.

SceneNet [Transfer Learning, VGG19, CNNs, Python, Flutter, Dart, FastAPI, Heroku]

December 2021

- Scenery detection through an Android application achieved by training VGG-19 on 10,000+ images belonging to 67 categories.
- Achieved 96% training accuracy, 64% cross-validation accuracy, and developed a standalone public API for the model.

## Volunteering / Mentoring

#### PyHEP (Python in High Energy Physics) Hackashop 2022

September 2022

 Collaborated with PyHEP organisers to mentor at a hackathon+workshop (hackashop) conducted for Python's High Energy Physics ecosystem.

#### Google Summer of Code

May - September 2022

• Mentored students under PyBaMM, NumFOCUS, on projects involving, but not limited to, documentation, DevOps, parameterisation, and visualization.

#### Relevant Skills

Languages:	Python (proficient)   Julia (proficient)   Dart (proficient)   C/C++   Java   JavaScript
${\bf Frameworks/Libraries:}$	Tensorflow   PyTorch   spaCy   NLTK   Tesseract-OCR   FluxML-Ecosystem   DeepXDE PyData-Ecosystem   SciML-Ecosystem   Flutter   FastAPI   NodeJS
Platforms and Tools	Linux   Heroku   Google Cloud   Elasticsearch   Kibana   Shell Scripting   Docker   CI/CD
Research Interests:	Deep Learning   Machine Learning   Scientific Machine Learning   Open Source Research Software

## Languages

Hindi (mother tongue), English (fluent), German (basic), Punjabi (conversational)